yeah so you often
um
you often see the suitors
in the suttas contentment being
mentioned as something to develop
is something to um
to cultivate
and um and protect so the question there
really is uh what kind of attitude
do you have towards
your own contentment is it something you
regard as
as given just sort of uh that you're not
responsible for as you know you can't
help it whether you're contented or
discontented or is it something that you
can actually make the effort towards
protect it
develop it further um make it increase
if it's sort of uh
not that
present the whole point is to to to
recognize that actually it is something
you can do
and it's something you can
learn how to be so as a suit as often
after mention it it is something you can
cultivate and it's actually
necessary for practice because
for practice because
content and discontent are the
are rooted in the mind so their states
of mind they're not dependent on the
circumstances so yes sure sometimes circumstances are
so yes sure sometimes circumstances are
absolutely not conducive for the
practice and you should not be content
with those
but then the time will come where um
there is no particular external reason
for your discontent like everything is
fine health is fine you you have enough food
health is fine you you have enough food
seclusion you're not being
overwhelmed by the elements and so on by
things you have to deal with
yet the mind is not content the mind is
restless the mind is looking for uh
different things change of the
environment and so on and that's that's
what you need to recognize then that
that's the problem now that the mind
cannot be
contented with things that are actually
suitable for the goal that you are clear
about so whether a monk or a lay
so whether a monk or a lay
you you should well you should always be
reviewing your situation as if it's
is it still supporting for the practice
uh is it still supporting for the
precepts um is it
um is it
too challenging is it is it making
things too too tempting too hard to
uphold if things are
if things are
not
not going in the direction of of of
making your life harder
making a practice harder
then you should also keep an eye on your
mind so it does not become discontented
with uh with things that are otherwise
fine so so
um
that's why
contentment is deep down it's actually
learned so you know fundamentally the
mind that's um that has developed more
can be contented even with things you
know even with like a loss of health and
so on
because uh as i said it is rooted in the
mind the state of mind that doesn't um
doesn't resist that's fundamentally what
contentment is
um so you do wanna and then it means
you're basically at ease and uh in a
state of equilibrium regardless of
what you're going through
so that way that's why contentment
should should could also be made into
like a goal to strive for
so you will be contented with things
internally so
so
and even if sometimes you choose to say
change the environment because
maybe it ceased to be suitable for the
practice and you you see directly how it
relates to
you know the lack of progress let's say
like that even then you can remain
contented internally even with the
change even with with with acting
towards the change that is necessary
um
so you can be contented contacting with
uncertainty contended with lack of control all these
contended with lack of control all these
things are pretty much come down on the
level of that um
accepting them on the level of your mind
and uh not not necessarily um
ignoring them or or just pretending to
go with the flow or something
no you might sometimes have to interrupt
the flow sometimes you might to do
things and so on but either way whether
you're with the flow or or against it
in terms of your environment you should
be contented internally
so
that's why the clearer the nature of
things become the nature of change
unknown ability and so on
the uh
the more effortlessly contented you
would be
being contented with little with
fewerness of desires um
with uh with seclusion and so on so um
all these goals
towards the developing a certain type of
environment such as you know not
socializing and
chasing sensuality keeping the precepts
you need to learn how to be contented
with because obviously the mind wants to
go with the pull of desires and so on
so that's why
once you do establish environment on the
basis of your discernment such as or
this environment is good for me
this environment is good for practice
does not necessarily make me feel
inspired or pleasant because solitude is
hard if it's not learned
um
abstaining from from pursuing uh
essential desires is hard if it's not
developed and so on but
i will sustain it and then i will learn
how to be contented with that and that's
where the practice will take a whole new
level that's the kind of you know
finding joy learning how to find joy in
solitude and non-sensuality and joys of
renunciation that's not going to happen
automatically or naturally or something
because naturally sensuality is the
direction the mind wants to go
company is the direction the mind wants
to go and that's why you're liable to
suffering so going against that grain
so going against that grain
is something you first need to take on
either faith out of underst under out of
the intellectual understanding that that
it is something that can
um
result in greater good for yourself and
others such as liberation
and then you actually have to learn how
to be contented with and protect that
environment and as i said in the beginning just
and as i said in the beginning just
don't confuse that
for learning to ignore things that are not
learning to ignore things that are not
suitable so you should not be contented
with centrality and you should not be
contented with the environment that's
conducive sensuality you should not be
contacted with socializing
depending on other people for your
emotional support that's not something
you should be contented with because
that is um
very much uh rooted in
in suffering and it's certainly
perpetuating the basis that is making
you liable to suffering so
learn to be contented
with things that you know are conducive
to for peace for dispassion for
disenchantment for seclusion
um for liberation pretty much for for
for non-dependence on any external or
internal factor for that matter
so so that's that's the goal to be
contented with and uh
and uh
and then yeah sometimes you probably
have to you know you will catch yourself
whereby things are very conducive for practice
things are very conducive for practice
there's nothing
there's nothing you have to deal with or
address yet
yet
you find your mind in a state of
discontent you find your mind in a state
of
not being settled or happy
and um
and all you need to do then is just
you know make some effort and and
contemplate the reasons for that
as in not look for faults but look for
the reasons for mine being discontent in
the environment that's otherwise you
know quite uh suitable for for content
um and then um actually yeah just uh
just
refrain from those thoughts they would
be fueling the discontent such as as i
said looking for faults
finding negative in
irrationally finding negative in in in
in things around you that are not
otherwise so
so
um and then just uh
sustain that awareness endure that
awareness that the mind is in a state of
discontent while there is no reason for
it to be
and as i said make sure you don't
welcome that discontent feel it further
think on account of it carelessly and it
will have to fade because it does
require that irrational discontent requires
that irrational discontent requires
equally irrational maintenance
so you need to be providing support you
need to be providing um
thoughts that are adding more to that
context of discontent
don't don't give in to that irrational
fault finding
um that has to be the basis for
discontent pretty much always
um so if it's not a factual basis for
discontent such as unsuitable
environment then it would be the
then it would be the
um your own fault-finding mind
there would be the reason for discontent
always you know thinking oh well he will
be better like this or better like that
and there is no end to that that's where
it's it's a kind of a trap mara's
daughter's trap as the suitors would say
discontent is one of the
one of the ways to to basically fall
away from the wholesome skillful context
even if you're in a very skillful
environment and then they keep living
basically in a very very uh unskillful
framework so you might still be
restrained and so on and not engaging in
centrality and secluded but if
fundamentally on top of that the mind
does not develop the framework of
contentment there will be blocking the progress
there will be blocking the progress
there will be preventing the context
from from that fulfillment
so even in the
in a layman's setting um
obviously you know with its own
limitations um
um
you you you can still
um on the basis of your precept
recognize what environment is suitable
for the precept and then try and uphold
such environment they will they will
make your restraint and renunciation
easier or at least more sustainable
and then
and then don't think your work ends
there either because
the mind will not necessarily even if
you do it even if you protect your
environment even if you keep your
presets the mind will not necessarily uh
grow to like it the mind will not
necessarily be contented with it
so
if you do sustain your effort and as i
said if you then become aware of your
protrudes discontent then you can
actually slowly
learn how to experience the pleasure of
enunciation which is which is what
contentment is
and actually start to prefer
um
renunciation precepts seclusion as i
said even within the limited framework
of overlay setting still the contentment
is necessary to be developed upon
the uh
the right and skillful behavior that
you've been cultivated beforehand
so when you become contented with such
such a lifestyle then obviously
um
the pressure
of sensuality that goes against their
lifestyle the pull of society the
the company will
will lessen because you are actually
preferring the opposite now you're not
just you know through a determination
and inspiration making the effort to go
against the grain you're becoming quite
contented quite happy in living against
the grain
and that's where the practice becomes
more effortless and and yeah that can be
developed then even further and so on
so that's why contentment is important
as a mental factor
and uh yeah that's why often the buddha
will talk about it because it is it is
something that everybody will have to
address at some point
um so don't just expect mind to be
contented on its own or if it is
contended on its own you still need to
do the work and review it and check
is there contentment there because of
the true recognition that this
environment is good for me and my sense
restraint is supported and renunciation
supported or are you contented just because you
or are you contented just because you
know there's some central basis or
something that the mind is actually
still delighting in and you're confusing
that for the right type of contentment
so
whether the mind is contented or not you
need to keep reviewing whether the mind
is contented or not and the reasons for
that contentment and if it's if they're
suitable and wholesome and skillful sure
you protect you keep you keep um you
keep being aware of that context but if
they're not that's where you kind of
rewrite them and you prevent your mind
from from dwelling on the negative
aspects or the central aspects and try
to basically
uh replace them with with the wholesome
uh contemplations and skillful aspects
they were basically would be revolving
around enunciations renunciation and
learning how to
how to like it pretty much in plain
terms